Neil V. Rosenberg bluegrass music collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Neil V. Rosenberg bluegrass music collection 1923-1985 1948-1985
AFC 2002/009
Rosenberg, Neil V.
approximately 2942 items
6 containers
approximately 1755 sheets
48 document files (DOC, DOCX, PDF, TXT): digital
273 reels: analog, 3 3/4 and 7 1/2 ips, 2 track; 7 in., 5 in., and 3 in.
34 sound cassettes: analog
786 sound files (AIF, MP3, WAV): digital
5 photographs: black and white; 5 in. x 8 in.
39 photographs: color transparencies (slide format); 35 mm
2 photographs: digital, color, JPG
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of compilation audio tape recordings; concert recordings from 1954-1969; and dubs of bluegrass radio programs, singles, and LPs.
Provenance
Neil V. Rosenberg; donation; 2002, 2014, 2019, 2023.
Brian Miksis; donation; 2013.
Accruals
Accruals from Neil Rosenberg were received in 2014, 2019, and 2023. Future accruals are expected.
Associated Materials
Tapes with original numbers 12-15, 106, and 281-290 were acquired as part of the Redwood Canyon Ramblers collection (AFC 2011/011).
Related Material
Related collections at the American Folklife Center, Library of Congress:
Alan Lomax Ohio and Indiana collection (AFC 1938/004)
Bascom Lamar Lunsford recording project, 1949 (AFC 1949/010)
Mike Seeger recordings, 1982 (AFC 1982/004)
Tennessee-Tombigbee Waterway Folklife Project collection, 1977-1988 (AFC 1985/035)
Neil V. Rosenberg interview with David A. Taylor (AFC 2002/030)
Jun-ichi Yamada collection of bluegrass recordings (AFC 2008/024)
Redwood Canyon Ramblers collection (AFC 2011/011)
Oscar Brand collection (AFC 2012/041)
Related collections at other repositories:
[United States, Indiana, Bean Blossom and Massachusetts, Worchester, 1954-1964], 64-038-F, Archives of Traditional Music, Indiana University, Bloomington https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/1395572
[United States, Indiana, Bloomington and Illinois, Urbana, 1963-1965], 66-147-F, Archives of Traditional Music, Indiana University, Bloomington https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/1395541
[United States, Indiana, Zionsville, 1964], 64-041-F, Archives of Traditional Music, Indiana University, Bloomington https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/1395553
[United States, Indiana, Bloomington, 1965], 66-173-F, Archives of Traditional Music, Indiana University, Bloomington https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/2064829
[Indiana, Brown County, 1965-1966], 14-203-F, Archives of Traditional Music, Indiana University, Bloomington https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/14763499
[United States, Indiana, Bloomington, 1966], 66-029-F, Archives of Traditional Music, Indiana University, Bloomington https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/2064827
[United States, Indiana, Bean Blossom, 1966], 66-192-F, Archives of Traditional Music, Indiana University, Bloomington https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/2064854
Neil V. Rosenberg Collection-502, Archives and Special Collections, Memorial University Libraries, Memorial University of Newfoundland https://collections.mun.ca/digital/collection/ead/id/668
Access and Restrictions
The Neil V. Rosenberg bluegrass music collection is open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Alternate Formats
Selected sound recordings in the Neil V. Rosenberg bluegrass music collection exist in both analog and digitized formats. Digitized versions were created by donor Brian Miksis as part of his "Redwood Canyon Ramblers Archive" digital project. Miksis edited them to enhance quality, and he created derivatives: high-resolution (aif or wav), medium-resolution CD pre-tagged (aif), and low-resolution mp3 pre-tagged (mp3) versions. See notes in Series 3.
Biographical Note
Neil V. Rosenberg
Neil V. Rosenberg (born 1939, in Seattle, Washington), grew up in Olympia, Washington, Los Alamos, New Mexico, and Berkeley, California. From age seven he studied violin, and later studied guitar and voice. His studies at Oberlin College (where he earned a B.A. in history) overlapped with his time as co-founder of the Redwood Canyon Ramblers. After graduation from Oberlin he attended Indiana University (where he earned his M.A. and Ph.D. degrees in folklore). Throughout this time he remained active as a musician and, with the banjo as his primary musical instrument, he played at the Brown County Jamboree in the early 1960s. His writing career from the mid-1960s has focused on bluegrass music history, and he has written critically acclaimed books including Bluegrass: A History (1985; revised 2005), Bluegrass Odyssey: A Documentary in Pictures and Words, 1966-86 (2001), and Bluegrass Generation: A Memoir (2018), as well as album liner notes and scholarly articles. His teaching career includes work at Indiana University (1966-1968) and Memorial University of Newfoundland (1968-2004). In Canada, as in the U.S., Rosenberg developed, founded, and mentored various musical endeavors: co-founder of the bluegrass band Crooked Stovepipe; host of a weekly bluegrass music show (broadcast on radio station CKIX-FM (St. John's, Newfoundland and Labrador, Canada); and numerous other achievements that served to draw and maintain a lively interest in the genre and history of bluegrass music. In 2014, he was inducted into the Bluegrass Hall of Fame.
Brian Miksis
Brian Miksis, a sound mixer with over 15 years of experience, digitized the recordings in this collection, and provided detailed metadata on the process and result. He has co-researched and produced an early history of Jerry Garcia's bluegrass roots, entitled Before the Dead (2018), and authored "An introduction to the Redwood Canyon Ramblers Archive".
Scope and Content
Collection of compilation audio tape recordings made from dubs of bluegrass 78 rpm discs, 45 rpm discs, LPs, radio airchecks, concert recordings, and interviews, in a series titled Bluegrass Anthology, some recordings are undated, some are dated 1948-1964. Plus a numerical series of concert recordings made by Neil V. Rosenberg and others at the Bean Blossom Festival, Mockingbird Hill Park, Club 47, Oberlin College, University of Illinois, Purdue University, in Berkeley, California; in Bloomington, Indiana, and other locations, from 1954-1969; plus various dubs of bluegrass radio programs, singles, and LPs.
Arrangement
The Neil V. Rosenberg bluegrass music collection is organized in three series:
Series 1. Tennessee-Tombigbee Folklife Survey and related materials
Series 2. Correspondence and contacts
Series 3. Sound recordings
Filepaths and digital files can be found in afc2002009_dc001. Please see the AFC reference staff for access.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Allen, Red, 1930-1993; Berline, Byron; Hambly, Scott; Monroe, Bill, 1911-1996; Monroe, Charlie; Rosenberg, Neil V.; Stringbean, 1915-1973; Wakefield, Frank; Watson, Doc; Wiseman, Mac
Organizations
Barrier Brothers; Bean Blossom Bluegrass Music Festival.; Blue Grass Boys; Carroll County Country Boys; Carter Family (Musical group); Country Gentlemen (Musical group); Foggy Mountain Boys; Freight & Salvage Coffee House (Berkeley, Calif.); Jim and Jesse; Kentucky Colonels (Musical group); Lorain County String Band; McCormick Brothers; New River Ranch (Md.); Osborne Brothers; Pigeon Hill Boys; Plum Creek Boys; Redwood Canyon Ramblers; Reno & Smiley; Stanley Brothers; Stoneman Family (Musical group)
Subjects
Bluegrass music.; Bluegrass musicians--United States--Interviews.; Folk music--United States.; Old-time music.
Places
Anderson (Ind.), event place.; Beanblossom (Ind.), event place.; Oberlin (Ohio), event place.; Rising Sun (Md.), event place.; Tennessee-Tombigbee Waterway (Ala. and Miss.)--Social aspects.
Titles
Brown County Jamboree (radio program); Grand ole opry (Radio program)
Form/Genre
Country music radio programs; Field recordings.; Radio airchecks
Container List
- Series 1: Tennessee-Tombigbee Folklife Survey and related materials
  Materials associated with efforts to create a fieldwork project to document the socio-economic impact of the creation of the Tennessee-Tombigbee Waterway.
  - Correspondence and research materials (1/2), circa 1960-1979 (Box-folder 1/1)
    Collected for Rosenberg's report on the impact of Federal public works projects on the folk culture of America and the ways in which the Archeological and Historic Preservation Act (Public Law 93-291) can mitigate that impact of July 16, 1979. Report is in #9. Approximately 200 pages. Original folder number: 1. See Box-Folder 1/2 for the balance of this folder's contents. No original folder heading.
  - Correspondence and research materials (2/2), circa 1960-1979 (Box-folder 1/2)
    See notes for Box-Folder 1/1.
  - Folklife Foundation bill, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 1/3)
    Includes Julia Butler Hansen correspondence which came to the attention of Ralph Rinzler in 1979, and who referred to it at the AFC Board meeting that led to the cancellation of the project. Approximately 20 pages. Original folder number: 2.
  - Tenn-Tom maps, 1974, 1978 (Box-folder 1/4)
    5 items. Original folder number: 3.
  - Tenn-Tom enabling legislation, January 4-5, 1979 (Box-folder 1/5)
    Notes on talk with Alan Jabbour. 1 page. Original folder number: 4.
  - Tenn-Tom press, 1979 (Box-folder 1/6)
    Mainly from 1979 boondoggle scandal. 9 items. Original folder number: 5.
  - Budget for Tennessee-Tombigbee Folklife Survey, October 4, 1978 (Box-folder 1/7)
    27 pages. Original folder number: 6. Original folder heading: Tenn-Tom October 4, 1978 Budget.
  - Tennessee-Tombigbee Folklife Survey project proposal and related documentation (1/2), September 1978-January 1979 (Box-folder 1/8)
    Correspondence, notes (including notes from phone conversations), diaries, documents. Approximately 50 pages. Original folder number: 7. Original folder heading: Tenn-Tom September 1978-January 1979.
  - Tennessee-Tombigbee Folklife Survey project proposal and related documentation (2/2), January 1979-April 1979 (Box-folder 1/9)
    Continuation of folder 7. See notes for Box-Folder 1/8. Approximately 70 pages. Original folder number: 8. Original folder heading: Tenn-Tom in progress.
  - AFC Report, 1979 (Box-folder 1/10)
    The research, along with another copy of this report, is in Box-Folder 1/1 and Box-Folder 1/2. Alan Jabbour's handwritten comments here. 15 pages. Original folder number: 9.
  - Tenn-Tom: the debate, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 1/11)
    Includes AFC Tenn-Tom Project chronology, the Folklife Act materials from 1976 (originally in Box-Folder 1/2 ) and, mainly, February 1979 correspondence sent by folklorists to Alan Jabbour prior to the AFC board meeting that led to the cancellation of the project. Approximately 80 pages. Original folder number: 10. Original folder heading: Tenn-Tom: The Debate (Also: Public Law 94-201).
  - Post-AFC Tenn-Tom, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 2/1)
    Correspondence, documents, newsletters. Approximately 70 pages. Original folder number: 11. Original folder heading: 1979-80 Post AFC Tenn-Tom.
  - Notes on Tenn-Tom for the Public Sector Discussion Group, February 5, 1985 (Box-folder 2/2)
    The group was formed when Memorial University of Newfoundland Graduate Studies Committee turned down the seminar proposal. 6 pages, handwritten in pencil. Original folder number: 12. Original folder heading: Notes on Tenn-Tom for Public Sector Discussion Group, February 5, 1985.
  - Tennessee-Tombigbee Waterway project and local involvement, 1978-1979, undated (Box-folder 2/3)
    Documents, letters, notes, and related documentation regarding efforts to involve and employ local workers in the construction of the waterway and on related initiatives. Circa 40 pages. Original folder number: 14. Original folder heading: Minority Peoples Council/Federation of Southern Cooperatives/Miles College-Eutaw [Alabama].
  - Tenn-Tom contract draft, January 1979 (Box-folder 2/4)
    Draft of the contract between AFC and the Department of the Interior's Interagency Archaeological Services to work together on the projected Tennessee-Tombigbee Waterway Folklife Project. Approximately 20 pages. Original folder number: 16 (mistakenly written "15" on the folder itself). Original folder heading: Tenn-Tom Contract draft (1).
  - Tenn-Tom name lists, circa 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2/5)
    Lists of names, CV of potential fieldworker, etc. 14 pages. Original folder number: 17.
  - Tenn-Tom phone call logs, May 1, 1979 (Box-folder 2/6)
    Handwritten, pencil; Bill Ferris (2 pages), Henry Glassie (2 pages), Barre Toelken (1 page), John Szwed (2 pages). Original folder number: 18.
  - DC January (plus diary), 1979 (Box-folder 2/7)
    Handwritten notes in spiral-bound notebook. 30 pages. Original folder heading: DC January 1979 (+Diary)."
  - Final budget and contract, January 22, 1979 (Oversize folder OV1)
    Approximately 50 pages, in a legal-size accordion folder. Original folder number: 19.
  - Tourist brochures for Columbus, Mississippi, undated (Box-folder 2/8)
    Tourist brochures collected by Carl Fleischhauer. 7 items. Original folder number: 15. Original folder heading: Way Down in Columbus Mississippi.
  - AFC Board meeting photos, possibly February 23, 1979, Carl Fleischhauer; 5 black and white photos: 5 in. x 8 in. (Box-folder 5/7)
    Includes photos of the following individuals: Archie Green (in the wide shot, with his back to the camera) talking to the board, and in the one vertical shot. Benny Keel (archeologist, and government official, with dark hair and a moustache), Jane Sapp (woman), and Wayland Hand (finger in the air). According to Carl, subsequent to this meeting Alan Jabbour decided not to proceed with the project.
  - Columbus, Mississippi, Carl Fleischhauer; 39 photographs: color transparencies: 35 mm (slide format) (Box-folder 5/8)
    These may be duplicates of photos in Tennessee-Tombigbee Waterway Folklife Project collection (AFC 1985/035).
- Series 2: Correspondence and contacts
  Materials include coverage of both the Tennessee-Tombigbee project and separate, music-related pursuits.
  - Correspondence with Bill Ferris (Center for the Study of Southern Culture), November 1978-February 1981 (Box-folder 2/9)
    Includes FSG Library Sale. Contents include correspondence and materials relating to various folk festivals and other projects. Approximately 150 pages. Original folder number: 13. Original folder heading: Bill Ferris/Center for the Study of Southern Culture (TENN TOM). November 1978-February 1981.
  - Resource people, A-F, undated (Box-folder 2/10)
    5 x 8 file cards. One card per person, organized alphabetically. 1 1/2 inch stack of cards. Original unit designation: Resource People.
  - Resource people, G-N, undated (Box-folder 2/11)
    See notes for Box-Folder 2/10.
  - Resource people, O-Z, undated (Box-folder 2/12)
- Series 3: Sound recordings, Digital files are located in afc2002009_dc001. Please see the AFC reference staff for access.
  Neil Rosenberg collected sound recordings for his own research, building a reference library of live recordings and studio recordings (including dubs of commercial recordings). Some of the recordings were sent to him as a gift or by request; the sources are noted if known.
  Brian Miksis digitized selected sound recordings and documentation, making high-resolution and lower-resolution surrogates. See Digital surrogates of selected recordings in Series 3. Song lists and production notes listed below are his own, compiled from his own research, observations while digitizing the recordings, and guidance from Neil Rosenberg, especially when the pitch needed adjustment to restore the audio quality.
  The archivist used a combination of Rosenberg's detailed inventories and information on tape boxes to create a list of contents per recording, and made additions and corrections based on further research. In addition, Rosenberg provided subsequent edits to the information. The documentation includes the names of those people who gave him tapes, identified in this finding aid as the "source." According to Rosenberg's documentation, items assigned the IDs SR256, SR268, and SR278 were deaccessioned from his collection prior to its arrival at AFC. He also noted that the ID SR262 was inadvertently not assigned to any recording, and the recording with the ID SR024 was loaned to someone but not returned.
  The original inventory includes tapes numbered 12-15, 106, 281-290. These are part of the Redwood Canyon Ramblers collection (AFC 2011/011).
  - Inventory of recordings (Box-folder 3/1-12)
    Contents of Rosenberg's three-binder comprehensive, item-level inventory of recordings in his collection, which includes original and photocopied documentation about songs, performers, venues, locations, and dates.
  - Manuscripts from audio containers, undated (Box-folder 3/13)
    Folders 1 of 14 folders. See Box-Folders 4/1-7 and Box-Folders 5/1-6.
  - Manuscripts from audio containers, undated (Box-folder 4/1-7)
    Folders 2-8 of 14 folders. See Box-Folder 3/13 and Box-Folders 5/1-6.
  - Manuscripts from audio containers, undated (Box-folder 5/1-6)
    Folders 9-14 of 14 folders. See Box-Folder 3/13 and Box-Folders 4/1-7.
  - Empty audio tape containers (Box 6)
    Original tape boxes for SR016, SR019, SR022, SR025, and SR047.
  - Bluegrass Anthology 01, AFC 2002/009: Bluegrass Anthology 01; RXI 0225; 1 sound tape reel (Side 1: 00:31:55, Side 2: 00:31:50): analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in.
    - Side 1
      - Dub of commercial recordings by various artists
        - "Gotta Travel On" - Bill Monroe, November 25, 1961
          Recorded at the Grand Ole Opry.
        - "Shady Grove" - Bill Monroe, November 25, 1961
        - "Worried Man Blues" - Flatt and Scruggs, January 6, 1962
        - "Cotton Fields" - Mother Maybelle and the Carter Sisters, January 6, 1962
        - "Matthew 24" - Wilma Lee and Stoney Cooper, January 6, 1962
        - "Cotton Fields" - Bill Monroe, January 6, 1962
        - "On A Cold Winter Night (Wreck of the Number Nine)" - J.E. Mainer's Mountaineers, 1936
          Victor (record label)
        - "Riding On That Train 45" - Wade Mainer, Zeke Morris, Steve Ledford, 1937
        - "Darling Corey" - Monroe Brothers, 1936
        - "Walk in the Gospel Way" - Bryant Wilson Trio, 1958
          Adair A2027 (CP-1605)
        - "Get Lost, You Wolf" - Hylo Brown, 1955
          Capital F3124 (45-13120)
        - "Freight Train Boogie" - Delmore Brothers, 1946
          King EP222 (KEP-46)
        - "Brown's Ferry Blues" - Delmore Brothers, 1947
        - "Hillbilly Boogie" - Delmore Brothers, 1946
          King EP222 (KEP-45)
    - Side 2
      - Dub of commercial recordings by various artists
        - "Little Birdie" - Stanley Brothers, August 5, 1956
          Recorded at Silver Creek
        - "Ho Honey Ho" - Osborne Brothers, June 30, 1957
          Recorded at New River Ranch
        - "Pretty Polly" - Osborne Brothers, June 30, 1957
        - "Willow Garden" - Osborne Brothers, June 30, 1957
        - "Shady Grove" - Flatt and Scruggs, possibly 1963
        - "John Hardy" - Ola Belle, September 16, 1956
        - "John Henry" - Charlie Monroe, May 27, 1956
        - "Paul and Silas" - Charlie Monroe, May 27, 1956
        - "Roane County Prison" - Stanley Brothers, September 1957
          Recorded at Fort Royal, Virginia
        - "Banks of the Ohio" - Blue Sky Boys, 1936
          Bluebird 6480
        - "Swing Low, Sweet Chariot" - Flatt and Scruggs, September 1957
          Recorded at Sunset Park
        - "Red Wing" - Osborne Brothers, 1958
          WWVA. This song was probably recorded from "Wheeling Jamboree," broadcast on WWVA, Wheeling, West Virginia).
        - "Blackeyed Susie" - Flatt and Scruggs, September 16, 1956
        - "Man of Constant Sorrow" - Stanley Brothers, April 16, 1957
          Recorded at Melody Ranch
  - Bluegrass Anthology 02, AFC 2002/009: Bluegrass Anthology 02; Marvin Hedrick (selections 9-21); RXI 0224; 1 sound tape reel (Side 1: 00:42:51, Side 2: 00:35:15): analog, 3 3/4 and 7 1/2 ips, half track; 7 in.
    - Side 1
      - Instrumentals And Ballads - Reno and Smiley, 1958
        Selections dubbed from King LP 579
        - "Limehouse Blues"
        - "Home Sweet Home"
        - "Remington Ride"
        - "Green Mountain Hop"
        - "Beer Barrel Polka"
        - "Richmond Ruckus"
        - "When You and I Were Young, Maggie"
        - "Tally-Ho"
      - Reno and Smiley, undated, Marvin Hedrick (selections 9-21)
        Radio show dubs. Continued on Side 2.
        - unidentified fiddle tune
        - "I'll Go Steppin' Too"
        - "Cumberland Gap"
        - "I'll Be No Stranger"
        - "The Letter Edged in Black"
        - "Sunny Mountain Chimes"
        - "You Better Get Right"
        - "Homesick"
        - "Walking in My Sleep"
        - "Family Bible"
        - "Walk and Talk"
        - "Molly and Tenbrooks"
        - "Talk of the Town"
    - Side 2
      - Reno and Smiley, undated
        Continued from Side 1
        - "Cruel Love"
        - "I'm So Happy"
      - Earl Taylor and The Stony Mountain Boys, undated
        - "Mule Skinner Blues"
      - Hack Johnson, undated
        - "Wildwood Flower"
        - "Pitfall"
        - "Feeling Low"
        - "Searching for a City"
      - Reno and Smiley show on WRVA, undated
        - "John Henry"
        - "I'll Never Take No For An Answer"
        - "You Gotta Be My Baby" - Ronnie Reno
        - "Under the Double Eagle"
        - "Little White-Washed Chimney" - Buddy Hogan
        - "Jesus Is Waiting"
        - "Katy Hill"
  - Bluegrass Anthology 03, AFC 2002/009: Bluegrass Anthology 03; RXI 0223; 1 sound tape reel (Side 1: 01:01:56, Side 2: 00:45:01): analog, 3 3/4 ips and 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in.
    - Side 1
      - Dubs of commercial recordings by various artists
        - "The Old Gospel Ship" - Lewis Family, 1959
          From the multi-artist LP Preachin' Prayin' Shoutin' and Singin' (Starday SLP 105)
        - "Lights in the Valley" - Lewis Family, 1959
        - "Prisoner's Song" - Bill Monroe, 1951
          Decca 46314
        - "Gotta Travel On" - Bill Monroe, 1958
          Decca 30809 (LP)
        - "Howdy, Neighbor, Howdy" - Reno and Smiley, 1958
          Dot LP
        - "For My Lord" - Carl Story, circa 1950s
          Starday SLP 101
        - "Long Journey Home" - Jim Eanes, 1952
          Blue Ridge Records 201-B
        - "Just a Little Talk With Jesus" - Virginia Trio, 1952
          Kentucky 510-B (LP)
        - "You Go To Your Church" - Virginia Trio, 1952
          Kentucky 510-A (LP)
        - "Mountain Dew" - Stanley Brothers, 1960
          King 5347 (LP)
        - "Old Rattler" - Stanley Brothers, 1960
        - "How Far to Little Rock" - Stanley Brothers, 1960
          King 5306 (45 rpm disc)
        - "Hold Whatcha Got" - Jimmy Martin, 1959
          Decca 30965 (LP)
        - "'Til the End of the World Rolls Round" - Flatt and Scruggs, 1954
          Columbia 4-21334 (45 rpm record)
        - "When the Angels Carry Me Home" - Flatt and Scruggs, 1960
          Columbia CL 1424 (LP)
        - "I'm On My Way to Canaan's Land" - Flatt and Scruggs, 1960
        - "You Can Feel It In Your Soul" - Flatt and Scruggs, 1960
        - "Take Me in the Lifeboat" - Flatt and Scruggs, 1960
        - "Joy Bells" - Flatt and Scruggs, 1960
        - "Dixie Hoedown" - Jim and Jesse, 1959
          Starday SLP 109
        - "Banjo Whiz" - Country Gentlemen, 1959
        - "Mandolin Tango" - Buzz Busby, 1959
        - "Mountain Hoedown" - Ken Clark, 1959
        - "Travelin' Dobro" - Country Gentlemen, 1959
        - "Border Ride" - Jim and Jesse, 1959
        - "Dixie Ramble" - Bill Clifton, 1959
    - Side 2